# R. Cem Varol

Southgate, N14, London • 7548 43 4748 cem.varol@gmail.com • Driving Licence B (1997) – A2 (2004)

Current workplace, QA Ltd, (London UK)

Former workplace, Eczacibasi Group is an international group of companies in *UK, USA, Germany, Turkey, Russia, China* which has 12.000+ Employees and 48 Companies within the group. Villeroy&Boch, VitrA-UK, Capintec, Monrol are members of the Eczacibasi Group.

## Personal Statement - Eligible to work in UK, Holding Indefinite Leave to Remain (ILR)

- A well-qualified Computer Engineer, with 20 years of experience on cloud technologies, messaging, communication, identity management, video conferencing, telephony and virtualization services.
- Skilled administrator with effective hands on experience in the IT industry with Cloud technologies (Microsoft Azure), Active Directory, Exchange, Enterprise Voice, Virtualization (Hyper-V, VmWare), URL Filtering, DLP.
- Meticulous Project Management Experience on juggling multiple tasks and working under pressure on different projects
- Certified **DevOps Engineer**, **Cloud Architect**, **Cloud Security Engineer**, holds the certifications below.
  - MCT Microsoft Certified Trainer
  - Azure Solutions Architect Expert
  - Azure DevOps Engineer
  - Azure Security Engineer
  - Azure Administrator
  - MCSD App Builder Azure Solution Developer
  - MCSE Cloud Platform & Architecture Azure Architect
  - MCSE Cloud Platform & Infrastructure Azure Infrastructure Designer
  - MCSE Productivity Exchange Server 2016

- MCSE Security
- MS Hyper-V and System Center Specialist,
- MCSE-Communication (Enterprise Voice, Skype for Business, Office 365)
- MCSE-Messaging –
   (Exchange all versions including 2016)
- MCSE-Windows Server –
   (2000-2003-2008-2012-2016)
- MCITP Enterprise Administrator
- MCSE+S, MCSE+M, MCTS, MCDBA
- CCNA Cisco Certified Network Associative

- Looking for a Position in the following areas;
  - Cloud Architect, accomplish the migration, or designing new cloud solutions for the enterprises.
  - Solution Architect, Designing and developing new technology solutions and integrating software for customers' enterprise applications. Designing /updating/upgrading tailored solutions for standard or inhouse applications on cloud Paas solutions of customers in order to address their needs.
  - **Security Architect**, adapting migrated or newly created cloud applications to comply with GDPR or other security regulations. Setting up robust security solutions.
  - **Pre-Sales Consultant,** provide solutions to customers, help sales teams to decide which services to sell, instruct IT operators for POCs or after sales.
  - **Devops Architect**, Supervising and collaborating with the development and operation teams on design and implementation of enterprise applications on Cloud Computing Systems.
  - **Devops Engineer,** collaboration with the development team to ensure the SDLC sustainability with the new developments. Holding a key communication role between operation and development teams.
  - Design/Architect Solutions based on Microsoft Products within Hands-On experience.
  - Security Project Manager, within experience as Azure Security Engineer
  - Project Manager, within 8 years of Experience on Budgeting, System Deliveries, Operations Management.
  - IT Manager, with long term experience of Managing Teams, Projects, People on Service Delivery and SLAs

# **Work Experience**

## **Foundation SP, Reading UK**

# Solution Architect – (07-2021 – Still working)

- Working as a Solutions Architect in order to evaluate customers' business needs, build, design, update or upgrade their environment and integrate information and solution systems which meet that need.
  - Solutions include Cloud Security, Software Design on Paas, Cloud Networking and DevOps.
- Analysing the business needs and providing a solution with the existing technology or designing a new technology by technical vision experience.
- Exploring business growth, scale for the future and how they will be maintained
- Understanding and mitigating the risk in 3<sup>rd</sup> party frameworks.
- Working with the customer IT specialists to support for their strategic IT planning.

# **QA Ltd, London UK**

## Senior Learning Consultant - (05-2015- 07-2021)

Providing coaching/training for the delegates all over the UK, on various sectors. As a Senior Learning Consultant with 20 years of experiences on Microsoft Technologies. *Teaching the Microsoft Certification courses listed below.* 

- Microsoft Certified: Azure Solutions –
   Azure DevOps DevOps Engineer
- Microsoft Certified: Azure Solutions –
   Azure Architect Expert
- Microsoft Certified: Azure Solutions –
   Azure Security Engineer
- Microsoft Certified: Azure Solutions –
   Azure Administrator
- MCSE Cloud Platform & Infrastructure –
   Azure Infrastructure Designer
- MCSD App Builder *Azure Solution Developer*

- MCSE Cloud Platform & Architecture –
   Azure Architect
- MCSE Productivity *Exchange Server 2016*
- MCSE Messaging Exchange 2016
- MCSE Messaging –Exchange 2013
- MCSE Communications Enterprise Voice
- MCSE Security on Windows Servers
- Windows Server 2016 First Wave, M10983
- MCSE Server Infrastructure 2016
- MCSE Server Infrastructure 2012-R2
- MS: Server Virtualization Hyper-V

# **Eczacibasi Group Co, CIO Office**

# IT - Project Manager - (06.2009 - 01.2015)

- Consulting Organizations manage, expand, and optimize their Microsoft infrastructure. Managing projects upgrading to the latest Active Directory and Exchange versions; allow reducing cost and complexity in their environment, while providing improved authentication and messaging services to their user and applications.
- Manage all features of projects, including project and budgeting plans, resource and task management from the planning and design stages to the documentation, training, and transition stages.
- Manage Communication Systems' Migration Projects. Exchange 2010-2013, LYNC 2013.
- Manage Virtualization project of 730 Servers within the Eczacibasi Group
- Develop and decide SLAs

## IT - Infrastructure Manager - Service Delivery Manager (Hands-On Experience)

- Act as a Pre-Sales Consultant to provide solutions for the group companies to provide new services for their requirements. (Providing Service Deliveries for 48 group companies)
- Design the Architectural Structure Active Directory, Exchange and LYNC services
- Pre-Sales actions on Lync, to be used SaaS for Audio/Video Conferencing solutions.
- Manage 12.000+ seated Microsoft Active Directory and Exchange environment.
- Manage 12.000+ seated Microsoft LYNC 2013 Migration Telephony Services, Video Conferencing and provide service platform
- Create detailed planning, procedures, and training documentation
- Develop custom solutions on Microsoft Exchange, Active Directory, SharePoint, LYNC 2013 and Forefront Identity Management.
- **Design and carry out**, cross–forests, Exchange and Active Directory consolidations, organization consolidations, organizations disjunctions, identity management, and directory (GAL) synchronization projects.
- Lead Manage the IT groups within the several Group Companies' IT staff on the relevant projects.
- Managed international Projects on infrastructure migration with multinational participants.

#### **Key Accomplishments (Hands-On Experience)**

- Managed a Data Center with 700+ Physical Servers, for 9 months by proxy.
- Designed, Implemented and Managed Disaster Recovery Solutions for the services.
- Migrated from various environments to the latest version of Active Directory, Exchange, and Windows systems.
- Managed all versions of Exchange and Active Directory Servers (hands-on experience).
- Managed all versions of OCS and LYNC Communication services, including IP Telephony and Enterprise Voice Services.
- Implementing and Installing LYNC SBA Services.
- Managed Virtualization Services Hyper-V and VmWare (hands-on Experience)
- Managed and implemented hardware resources such as HP EVA/Blade Servers, NetApp,
- Managed and implemented communication components such as ActiveSync, iOS Devices, BlackBerry Enterprise Servers (BES) and other enterprise technologies.
- Managed and implemented F5 Devices on Proxy/Reverse Proxy, Publish Applications, Load Balancing
- Created and managed ITIL, COBIT processes with CA Unicenter Service Manager Family.
- Implemented and managed Identity Management System (Microsoft ILM/FIM)

- Managed and implemented Symantec Brightmail SPAM Filtering and antivirus products for SMTP and Exchange messaging.
- Implemented and managed several Security Solutions, URL filtering, DLP.
- Antivirus Applications with Symantec End Point Protection Suite platform,
- VPN and Web Publishing with Microsoft UAG, ISA and TMG.
- Managed and implemented Corporate Portal Platform, with Microsoft SharePoint.
- Corporate Windows 7 and 8.1 and Office 2010-2013 Upgrade Project, Corporate Wide (Germany, France, UK, Russia, China, USA) on 12.000+ client computers.
- Open-Text Mail Archiving System, Corporate Wide (Germany, France, UK, Russia, China, USA)
- Villeroy-Boch AD and Exchange User/Mailbox Migration (500+ users), Germany
- VitraUK Branch Virtualization (Hyper-V)-UK

#### Recent Projects (Technical Architecture, Hands-On Experience)

- Oxford, UK Virtualization Project.
- Ramsey NY, Pittsburgh PA, USA Company services migration, Active Directory user accounts, Exchange mailboxes, used applications.
- *Pfalz, Germany* Company Services Migration, Active Directory user accounts, Exchange Mailboxes, computer accounts, file and application servers. (500+ users)
- *Cologne, Germany* Exchange Migration 500+ users
- Virtualization projects of 240+ with Hyper-V v1.0, v2.0, v3.0 and VmWare 3,5, 4, 4i, 5.0, 5.5
- **F5 BIG-IP** implementation project on all applications residing on DMZ.
- Migration from OCS 2007 to LYNC 2013 project with voice communications (VoIP), and content sharing.
   Replacing Siemens Telephone Centrals with LYNC 2013.
- Virtualization/Consolidation project of the Data Center within the VmWare technology.
- Implementation project of CA Asset Management Product.
- Migration project from Lotus Notes to Microsoft Exchange 2007.
- Upgrade project within 12.000+ users from Microsoft LCS to OCS Platform.
- All aspects of migration project of 12.000+ Mailboxes from Exchange 2007 to Exchange 2010 The design included
  a live and DR sited DAG deployment, implemented on VMware virtual machines, HP EVA and NetApp SANs.
- Mail Archiving Project with Open-Text Mail Archiving for Microsoft Exchange Platform. Including a live and DR sited infrastructure.
- Management of several Active Directory and Exchange Migration projects; Such as, Company joins, employee
  migration from other systems: including user accounts, applications, computer accounts and mailboxes. Smooth
  operations; users did not notice the difference, even on computer user profiles.
- All aspects of **Active Directory 2003 to 2008 R2, 2012 R2** migration project. A global migration on multi countries within Hyper–V virtualization technology.
- All aspects of Exchange 2003 to Exchange 2007 and 2007 to 2010 migration projects. The design included one primary site with a passive DR site, implemented on physical hardware, HP EVA and NetApp SANs. Within 12.000+ mailboxes, 5 TBs of data for Group Companies. Including 22 Active Directory domains and 24 Exchange sites' consolidation to four Domains and one Exchange site.
- All aspect of ITIL Processes, CA Unicenter Service Manager and Network&System Manager implementation project.
- Implementation project of Microsoft ForeFront UAG as VPN solutions.
- Several versions of WebSense implementation and upgrade projects. (6.x, 7.x, TRITON)
- Consulted implementation project of MS System Center Service Management Platform.
- Consulted migration project from Microsoft **SharePoint** 2007 to 2010.
- Migration project of Corporate Portal from IBM WebSphere to Microsoft SharePoint 2007.

## **Turkish Armed Forces Gülhane Military Medical Academy (GATA)**

#### Systems Architect - (08.2008-02.2009)

GATA Karanet (intranet) administration. Back–Up operations. Hospital Management Software Customization. VLAN modification. Websense Applications. Database System Disaster Recovery Operation, with Honour Certificate

## **Bilge Adam, Education and Consultancy**

#### **Corporate Consultant - (06.2006-06.2008)**

Supporting sales team **as Pre-Sales Consultant**, analysing the customer's technical infrastructure to **provide new offers** for upgrading and updating the systems or the services of the customers.

#### **Corporate Trainer**

**Training the IT staff** of the Bilge Adam partners and customers. Training the Trainers Microsoft Trainings. **Cisco Trainings**.

### **Netron, Education and Consultancy**

### Pre-Sales Training Consultant - (07.1999-04.2006)

Supporting and **guiding sales team** as a consultant, to decide and provide trainings for corporate customers' requirements.

#### **Training Programs Specialist - Corporate Trainer**

- Arranging the trainings' contents and adapt the contents to the students' knowledge.
- Consulting the trainers (Master Trainer) Train the Trainers.
- Microsoft Trainings. Training the IT staff of Netron's partners for the business partners.
- Siemens SBS project

## **Education**

## **Galatasaray University – 2014,**

# **Management Information Systems,**

#### **Key Skills gained:**

- Introduction to management information systems
- Decision analysis and its applications
- Corporate Reporting
- Information Management in organizations
- Data Mining
- Sales information communication technology
- Technology Management, Research & Development
- Business case reporting and its progress tracking with applications
- Customer relationship management and application projects
- Software quality and information systems quality
- Networks in information systems and its applications
- Human resources management
- Information technology governance
- Organization management and information technologies
- Database Management
- Information systems and project management

### Istanbul University - 2002,

## **Engineering Faculty** – Computer Engineering,

## **Key Skills gained:**

- Universal computer engineering courses.
- Computer Programming with, C, C#, C++, Java, PHP, Perl, CGI, ASP, Visual Basic, CORBA.
- Computer Design
- Project Management
- Network Programming
- System Programming
- Engineering Concepts

### **Hobbies & Interests**

- Keen interest in acting, attended different plays, "Romeo Juliet, from William Shakespeare, "Oscar, From Claude Magnier", "The River, from Jez Butterworth", "See How They Run, from Philip King" and some other different Turkish plays. Not for professional purposes.
- Basketball and cycling.